<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ioy out-joyed: or, Joy in overcoming evil spirits and evil men, overcome by better joy: set forth in a sermon at Martins in the fields, to the Right Honourable the Lords assembled in Parliament, upon the day of their solemn rejoycing and praising God, for reducing the city of Chester by the forces of the Parliament, under the command of Sr William Brereton, February 19. 1645. / By Joseph Caryl minister of the Gospel at Magnus neer London Bridge.</title>
            <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E323_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861303</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113435</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113435)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E323[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ioy out-joyed: or, Joy in overcoming evil spirits and evil men, overcome by better joy: set forth in a sermon at Martins in the fields, to the Right Honourable the Lords assembled in Parliament, upon the day of their solemn rejoycing and praising God, for reducing the city of Chester by the forces of the Parliament, under the command of Sr William Brereton, February 19. 1645. / By Joseph Caryl minister of the Gospel at Magnus neer London Bridge.</title>
                  <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for John Rothwel at the signe of the Sun and Fountain in Pauls Church-yard, and Giles Calvert at the signe of the Black-spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke X, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113435:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IOY OUT-JOYED: OR, <hi>Joy in overcoming evil ſpirits and evil men, Overcome by better Joy:</hi> SET FORTH IN A SERMON at <hi>Martins</hi> in the fields, to the Right Honourable the Lords Aſſembled in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> upon the day of their Solemn Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and praiſing God, for reducing the City of <hi>Cheſter</hi> by the Forces of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> under the Command of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> WILLIAM BR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>RETON, <hi>February</hi> 19. 1645.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Joſeph Caryl</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Magnus</hi> neer <hi>London</hi> Bridge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>John Rothwel</hi> at the Signe of the Sun and Fountain in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Signe of the Black-ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113435:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113435:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE The Houſe of PEERS Aſſembled in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE world is too narrow for our paſsions (we may ſoon over-joy or over-ſorrow the best or the worſt estate which earth affords or can inflict) What an <hi>Atome</hi> then is it to our underſtandings? The world is too little and too low-prized for the minde of the leaſt, of the pooreſt man, who hath the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a man: what <hi>A nothing</hi> then is it to (ſuch as <hi>yours</hi> are) <hi>Great and noble mindes?</hi> And yet (as inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as it is) they who have only the world to rejoyce in, ſhall not (ſhortly) have a world to rejoyce in. The faſhion of it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away daily, and the matter of it is of no long continuance. The beauty of it was stained in its infancy, and the frame of it must be conſumed when it is a few (who knowes how few) years elder. This ſhould call off our thoughts from eager earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purſuits, and pitch them upon a higher and more <hi>enduring ſubſtance.</hi> This ſhould provoke us to put the <hi>moon</hi> (all <hi>changeable excellencies</hi>) under our feet, and make us reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe till we are cloathed with the <hi>Sun,</hi> an <hi>eternall excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy?</hi> 'Twas the deſigne of the enſuing Sermon, to befriend ſouls with ſuch a change of cloathing: and to entice them into the joys of a <hi>name written in Heaven,</hi> that they might not too much read or rejoyce in any, (no not their own) on earth.
<pb facs="tcp:113435:3"/> I know the victories and ſucceſſes of a just warre, endebt us not only to Thankfulnes, but to Ioy. Such victories are the exactest pieces both of the wiſdom and power of God; God is called a <hi>man of warre,</hi> but nothing ſhews him <hi>more a God then warre.</hi> And among all warres, a warre with ſpirits, (though but with the ſpirits of men) ſhews most of God. The great promiſe of reſtoring <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is thus prefac'd. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, which ſtretcheth out the Heavens, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the foundation of the earth, and formeth the ſpirit of man within him,</hi> (Zech. 12. 1.) All reforming about ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, begins at the forming of ſpirits. Whether God forms ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, or breaks ſpirits (which will not receive his form) his work is admirable. God hath begun a warre with, and a work upon ſpirits in our dayes: Some ſpirits are beautifully formed, others are juſtly broken. T'is a duty to rejoyce in both, chiefly in the former. We muſt rejoyce (for the Angels in heaven do) when we hear the ſpirits of other men are formed, but the beſt cauſe of joy is when we finde our own are. How much ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the publike is reformed without, or how many ſoever are formed within, yet if any heart lie ruin'd, or life unſhap't, he may (in the midſt of all theſe joys and triumphs, for he ſhall) <hi>lie down in ſorrow.</hi> That <hi>your Lordſhips</hi> may have many <hi>rejoicing daies,</hi> and a <hi>rejoycing eternity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> That your <hi>Names</hi> may be written in the faireſt and greateſt letter which <hi>Honour</hi> can make on earth, and that they may be written in the fair-eſt and greateſt letter, which <hi>Glory</hi> Shall make in Heaven, is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humbly devoted Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113435:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED to the Right Honourable the Houſe of PEERS aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> Upon the Day of their ſolemne Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for the reducing of the City of <hi>CHESTER</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LUKE 10. 20.</bibl>
               <q>Notwithſtanding in this rejoice not, that the ſpirits are ſubject unto you: but rather rejoice becauſe your names are written in Heaven.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE King of Saints, and Captain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of our ſalvation <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> having called, commiſſion'd and ſent out twelve <hi>Apostles</hi> as great Commanders to ſubdue his native Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to himſelf, at the ſixth Chapter of this Goſpel: He at the firſt verſe of this, prepareth and ſendeth forth a band of <hi>ſeventy Auxiliaries,</hi> to proſecute and advance the ſame deſigne. <hi>After theſe things, the Lord appointed other
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113435:4"/> ſeventy alſo, and ſent them two and two before his face, into every City and place, whither he himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f would come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſhew that the weapons of their warfare were not carnall, but mighty through God, theſe <hi>ſeventy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning victors, report the ſucceſſe of their expedition, and ſhew Chriſt the Trophies of their conqueſt, at the 17 verſe; <hi>And the ſeventy returned again with joy ſaying, Lord, even the devils are ſubject unto us through thy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, ſaith Chriſt, I know it to be ſo; this is not a vain boaſt of valour, (like theirs, who will vaunt they have kill'd the Devil; and run ſtrange adventures, when they ſcarce dare look an enemy in the face,) I my ſelf can bear you wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that you have faithfully and effectually acted your commiſſion: the iſſues of your ſervice have been glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in mine eye. <hi>And he ſaid unto them, I beheld Satan like lightning fall from Heaven,</hi> verſ. 18. The powers of darkneſſe cannot ſtand before the Goſpel of light: <hi>The Devil, the prince of the ayr is no match for Chriſt; no nor for the meaneſt of the ſervants of Chriſt, who go forth armed with his name and power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe Chriſt found that theſe ſervants of his had managed their former commiſſion ſo well; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is ſo far from calling it in, that he inlargeth it at the 19 verſe; <hi>Behold, I give you power to tread on ſerpents and ſcorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing ſhall by any means hurt you.</hi> Go forth again in this armour of power with which I have girt you, and I warrant you <hi>ſword-free, and ſhot-free, nothing</hi> (either on earth or in hell) <hi>ſhall by any means</hi> (ſtrength or ſtratagem) <hi>hurt you;</hi> all the world will be againſt you, but I am with you, take courage, nothing ſhall hurt you: therefore on again in this warfare, you ſhall (as my ſelf) go forth <hi>conquering and to conquer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113435:4"/>
            <p>Now, who was able to bear ſuch a burden of honour from theſe paſt and promiſed victories with modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? How many by hearing a report of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts over other men, have been overcome with their own pride! <hi>It is an eaſier matter to gain ſucceſſes then to bear them well.</hi> Chriſt (who knows the meaſure of every ſpirit) ſeems to ſuggeſt, that even the good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of his Diſciples began to over-act upon theſe victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries over evil ſpirits. Hence he gives them an allay by counſel and caution, not to raiſe their joy too high upon this point. And more, he diverts their joy (which he ſaw ready to overſlow the banks of that chanell where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was) into another chanell, wide and capacious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to hold all the inundations of it: <hi>Notwithſtanding, in this rejoice not, that the ſpirits are ſubject unto you; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejoice in this, that your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſtay upon any anxious diviſion of the text; There are two clear parts in it: The one Corrective; The other Directive.</p>
            <p>The Corrective part lies in the firſt words, wherein Chriſt checks and ſtops the ſuſpected exceſſes of their joy, for victories gained over evil ſpirits: <hi>Notwithstanding, in this rejoice not, that the ſpirits are ſubject unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Directive part lies in the later words, ſhewing them a joy wherein there could be no exceſſe; <hi>but rather rejoice in this, becauſe your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Notwithſtanding, in this rejoice not.</hi>] Joy is the opening and dilatation of the heart upon the receiving of ſome preſent good thing; as ſorrow is the coarctation, the ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or locking up of the heart, upon the preſſure of ſome preſent evil. <hi>Rejoice not,</hi> that is, let not your hearts open too much in receiving this object. The negation is not abſolute, but only comparative; ſo it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113435:5"/> in the next clauſe, <hi>Rejoice not, but rather.</hi> He doth not forbid, but qualifie and moderate their joy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the ſpirits are made ſubject to you</hi>] Angels are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and they are either good or bad. That theſe ſpirits were bad Angels, we have warrant at the 17 verſe, <hi>The Devils are ſubject unto us.</hi> Theſe were once good Angels, Now they are fallen; and by their fall they have loſt their condition, but not their conſtitution; their honour, but not their nature, they are ſpirits ſtill. <hi>The ſpirits are made ſubject to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Subjection</hi> is two-fold: Either compulſory, or volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. The ſubjection here meant, is a compulſive ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: They are not ſubject to you as the Saints are to Chriſt, by a profeſſed ſubjection of their wills, but they are ſubject (as a ſlave to his Lord) whether they will or no, by an impoſed ſubjection. Good Angels faithfully ſerve the Saints; and evil Angels are made ſubject to them. The former are <hi>miniſtring ſpirits, ſent out for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good of thoſe who are the heirs of ſalvation:</hi> The later are kept by the power of Chriſt, and the miniſtry of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, from doing hurt to the <hi>heirs of ſalvation.</hi> To be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled for this is a great priviledge, yet the Diſciples muſt not rejoice greatly in this: In what then? Chriſt ſhews them a better and a nobler object of joy; <hi>But rather rejoice that your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are no literall records in the Court of Heaven, there is no pen or ink, no paper or parchment there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To be <hi>written in Heaven</hi> is only this, to be elected unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and adopted ſons of God, to an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints in light. <hi>Moſes</hi> of old ſpake this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>Exod. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 23. Blot me out of thy book which thou haſt written. David,</hi> in alluſion to this, phraſes a prayer againſt his enemies; <hi>Let them be blotted out of the book of the living,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113435:5"/> and not be written among the righteous,</hi> Pſal. 69. 28. And Chriſt promiſes the Sardian victor, That he will not <hi>blot his name out of the book of life,</hi> Rev. 3. 5.</p>
            <p>God is ſaid to have two books in Heaven. Firſt, He hath a book of thoſe things which we have done, or the <hi>book of conſcience,</hi> Rev. 20. 12. <hi>I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great ſtand before God: and the books were opened, and the dead were judged out of thoſe things which were written in the books according to their works.</hi> Secondly, He hath a book of what himſelf hath done, or the <hi>book of election,</hi> called often in Scripture <hi>the book of life,</hi> Phil. 4. 3 Rev. 13. 8. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. 8. c. 20. 15. c. 21. 27. c. 22. 19.</p>
            <p>Further, God may be ſaid to have in Heaven <hi>a black book,</hi> wherein every word is a blot, a blot fallen from the lives of wicked men here upon the earth. And he hath (as I may ſo ſpeak) <hi>a white book,</hi> a book written with the fair letters of all the holy acts which his Saints have done upon the earth.</p>
            <p>Again, God hath a <hi>book of death,</hi> wherein all the names of reprobates are written, with the gall and wormwood of his everlaſting wrath: And he hath <hi>a book of life</hi> in Heaven, written with the golden raies and beams of his own eternall love. Our being written in this book of life, is the matter of that exceeding joy, to which Chriſt calls his Diſciples in the text; <hi>But rather rejoice in this, that your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words thus opened, yeeld plenty of ſeaſonable and profitable inſtructions. Firſt this. <hi>Evil ſpirits are ſubject to the power of Chriſt working in his Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi> The Devil is ſubject not only to the immediate and perſonall power of Chriſt, but to his mediate and miniſteriall power. The ſubduing of the Devil was not a buſineſſe confined to that age wherein Chriſt ſojourn'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113435:6"/> on earth ſuch victories are obtained every day. Such conqueſts as the Diſciples obtained are very rare; And I intend not a diſcourſe about the poſſeſſion, or diſſpoſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of evil ſpirits: but there is an ordinary way of ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power of the Devil, in the miniſtration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. The Goſpel is the miniſtration of the holy Spirit, and therefore it muſt needs be victory over the evil ſpirit. Thus the unclean ſpirit is made to diſlodge. The Divel is ſeldom permitted to poſſeſſe the body of any man; but he poſſeſſes the ſouls of all wicked men. And though the Divel be caſt out of the ſouls of all beleevers, yet he never ceaſes to oppoſe their ſouls. Every time a ſinner is converted, an evil ſpirit is ſubdued; and every time a temptation is reſiſted by the Saints, an evil ſpirit is foiled. The Divel is a great prince, and he hath more then halfe the world his ſubjects; Many millions, and among them many Kings of the earth doe him homage, and ſtoop to his commands. But how great ſoever he is, and how many ſoever follow him, yet he is made to ſtoop to the leaſt of the Saints: That roaring Lion couches to them, and they tread upon this ſerpent. <hi>The God of peace bruiſes Satan under their feet,</hi> Rom. 16. 20. Beſides, as evil ſpirits are ſubdued, which work in, or againſt the ſouls of men; So evil ſpirits are kept from hurting and afflicting the bodies and outward eſtates of men. For as good Angels incamp about the godly to guard and protect them: ſo evil Angels incamp againſt the godly to anoy and vex them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If the power of Chriſt, to this day, did not maſter and ſubdue the power of thoſe evil ſpirits, they would make ſtrange confuſions in the world quickly.</p>
            <p>The Divels are under a twofold chaine; Firſt, under a chain of juſtice: So the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> at the ſixth verſe of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113435:6"/> his Epiſtle, <hi>They are reſerved in everlaſting chains,</hi> (they can never wear them out, or file them off) <hi>under darknes to the judgement of the great day.</hi> Secondly, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a chaine of providence, God lets them goe abroad, but never without this chain; He gives them ſcope, and checks them as himſelf pleaſes. Wicked men <hi>are led captive by Satan at his will,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 26. and Satan is led captive at the will of Jeſus Chriſt. He cannot act ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by himſelf or by his inſtruments, but as permitted; and if Chriſt oppoſe, both his power and the power of his inſtruments is ſtopt and broken. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lypt (Rev. 20. 1, 2.) <hi>Saw an Angel (Chriſt) come down from Heaven, having the key of the bottomleſse pit, and a great chain in his hand, and he laid hold on the dragon that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which is the Divel and Satan, and bound him a thouſand years, and caſt him into the bottomleſſe pit, and ſhut him up, and ſet a ſeal upon him, that he ſhould deceive the nations no more, till the thouſand years ſhould be fulfilled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and after that he muſt be looſed for a little ſeaſon.</hi> Opinions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are very various, about the preciſe time of Satans binding and looſing; But we may hence conclude an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious proof for this point in generall, That Satan is ſubject to the power of Chriſt. He bindes him from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the nations, and he can binde him from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling either perſons or nations.</p>
            <p>This magnifies the power of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he makes evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſubject. This is a conqueſt beyond all thoſe of the <hi>Roman Conſuls or Caeſars;</hi> there was never any of them that brought the Divel home in chains. Evil ſpirits were never dragged at their chariots of triumph. Thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours were themſelves captives to theſe ſpirits. And while they procured liberty for the common-wealth, they themſelves were the ſervants of corruption, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113435:7"/> ſlaves to Satan; <hi>for of whom</hi> (or by what) <hi>any maie is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, of the ſame is he brought in bondage,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 19.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This may encourage us in the greateſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties. If ſpirits are ſubject to the power of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the Saints; then, what is there in the world but may be ſubjected by this power, There is no power greater then the power of ſpirits. One ſpirit deſtroyed a mighty army in one night, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19. 35. Can fleſh and blood, can gates of braſſe and walls of ſtone ſtand out, when ſpirits themſelves muſt yeeld? Every creature hath its ſtrength in its ſpirits; There are corporall ſpirits, as well as ſpirituall ſpirits. There are ſpirits of the body, produced out of the matter, being the finer, purer and more ſublimate parts of it: ſpirits animall in the brain, vitall in the heart, and naturall in the liver, theſe are the ſtrength of our bodies. And there are ſpirits in things without life, Theſe ſpirits are their ſtrength alſo; the ſpirit of wine is the ſtrength of the wine, ſo of any other liquour. Spirits extracted are the ſtrength of any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance contracted into a narrow room. There is a ſpirit of a ſpirit. <hi>The ſpirit of the minde,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 23. <hi>Be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſpirit of your minde;</hi> This ſpirit of the minde is the ſtrength of the minde. To ſpend ſpirits is to ſpend ſtrength, and to get ſpirits is to get ſtrength, both of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and minde. When the Prophet would ſhew that the horſes of the Egyptians were weak, he ſaith, <hi>Their horſes are fleſh and not ſpirit,</hi> (Iſa. 31. 3.) and the Apoſtle to ſhew how ſtrong. Devils are, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 12. ſaith, <hi>We wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle not againſt</hi> (groſſe things) <hi>fleſh and blood,</hi> but againſt <hi>principalities and powers, againſt the rulers of the darkneſſe of this world, against ſpirituall wickednes in high places.</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall wickednes is wicked ſpirits: and becauſe they <hi>are ſpirits,</hi> therefore they <hi>are powers.</hi> In evil ſpirits there
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113435:7"/> is power, much more in good ſpirits, and moſt of all in <hi>the beſt ſpirit</hi> the Holy Ghoſt <hi>ye ſhall receive power, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Holy Ghoſt is come upon you,</hi> Act. 1. 8. whereſoever ſpirit is, there is power. The ſpirit of a man is of ſuch ſtrength that it is able to beare his infirmity; our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities are our heavieſt part. <hi>Nothing calls for more ſtrength then the bearing of our own infirmities, or the infirmities of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men.</hi> Yet while a man can hold up his ſpirit and maintain that, he may beare (and rejoyce in) the heavieſt burthen of his own outward infirmities. A ſtrong ſpirit ſtrengthens the weakeſt, and a weak ſpirit weakens the ſtrongeſt body or minde.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all is this, ſpirits are ſtrong, and evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are ſtronger then all fleſh, yet theſe are ſubject to the power of Chriſt; then never fear fleſh and blood, fire and ſword, when you heare ſpirits muſt ſubmit. When Chriſt would aſſure the Church that it ſhould ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all oppoſition, he promiſes <hi>the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it,</hi> Matth 16. 18. that is, the power of evil ſpirits ſhall not; and if the gates of hell cannot, ſurely gates of earth ſhall never prevail. We may be confident if ſpirits cannot, fleſh and blood ſhall not doe us any hurt, while Chriſt is with us. This leads us to the ſecond Obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is matter of joy to bring ſpirits, evil ſpirits into ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> The Diſciples paſſion was not without reaſon, when they rejoyced to ſee ſpirits ſtoop: it is no ſmall priviledge to make evil ſpirits ſtoop, whether they be evil ſpirits tempting and troubling without, or moving within us.</p>
            <p>It is matter of joy to ſubdue any reall enemy, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe, Firſt, who are moſt for number: Secondly thoſe, who are mightieſt in ſtrength; Thirdly thoſe, who are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113435:8"/> higheſt in place; Fourthly thoſe, who are ſubtilleſt in projecting; Fifthly thoſe, who are moſt malicious, and bloody in executing. All theſe meet in evil ſpirits. They are many, mighty, high, ſubtile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and malicious. <hi>The Devil is a legion by name, a Prince by his place; A Goliah, an Achit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phel, A Doeg, all joyn'd in one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a glorious victory to overcome a temptation to ſinne. Every time we doe ſo, we overcome a Devil: The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> encourages us, <hi>Reſiſt the Devil, and he will flee from you:</hi> that is, he will be ſubject to you. You drive away the Devil every time you ſtand it out in a temptation and ſtand faſt.</p>
            <p>It is a great victory to overcome the ſinnefull corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are in our own hearts; To overcome paſſion and corruption within, is like the overcoming of a temptation from without: The evil ſpirit is vanquiſhed in both. The <hi>Sadduces</hi> denyed all ſpirits (<hi>Act.</hi> 23. 8.) and others have affirmed, that good and evil ſpirits are onely good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil motions within us. I abominate the errour, and yet there is a truth ſomewhat like it. Good or evil motions within us, are (in a ſenſe) good or evil ſpirits; For as that which is borne of the good ſpirit is ſpirit (<hi>Joh.</hi> 3.) So that which is borne of the evil ſpirit is ſpirit too. Every evil motion in us is borne of the Devil; who though he be not the immediate parent of all ſuch motions, yet he was the immediate parent of that corruption from whence ſuch motions are derived. So that though theſe ſinfull paſſions are not thoſe ſpirits; yet they have the ſtrength and life of evil ſpirits in them. Hence <hi>Solomon</hi> puts the glory of a conqueſt over them, beyond the glory of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conqueſts; Pro. 16. 32. <hi>He that is ſlow to anger, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the mighty; and he that ruleth his ſpirit,</hi> (that is, who overcomes his ſinfull ſpirit, and makes it ſubject to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113435:8"/> him) <hi>is better then he that taketh a City.</hi> We are called to bleſſe God for taking a City this day: if we overcome our ſelves, and rule our own ſpirits, this is a more honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conqueſt, then that we bleſſe God for this day, the taking of a City, <hi>He that ruleth his ſpirit, is better then he that taketh a City.</hi> I beſeech you, ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, 1 Epheſ. 2. 11. As pilgrims and ſtrangers abstain from fleſhly lusts, which warre againſt the ſoul. Fleſhly lusts</hi> are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all enemies; <hi>Abſtaining from theſe,</hi> is victory over theſe; we kill them by fleeing from them. This is the greateſt warre, and the iſſues of it are of greateſt conſequence. It is more noble to ſubdue luſts within us, then Armies without us; And it is more advantage to us to conquer luſts then to conquer the world. <hi>Better be a Paul, then an Alexander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, It is matter of great joy when the evil ſpirits of men are overcome; This is the hardeſt part of our warre with men, and the beſt. Battels are but half won when onely the bodies of men are wonne; then it is a thorow victory when we are victours over their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. The counſel which that <hi>Indian Gymno-ſophiſt Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> gave <hi>Alexander</hi> about managing of his warre, was this; <hi>Get into the heart of your enemies Countrey,</hi> which he taught him by the embleam of a great Oxe-hide ſpread upon the ground: He adviſed <hi>Alexander</hi> to get into the heart of the Enemies Countrey. My humble advice to you, <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> is, <hi>to get into the heart of your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> While nothing is conquered but the bodies of men and Cities, you are but upon the borders of victory.</p>
            <p>There is a double conqueſt over ſpirits, one is the <hi>chaining of ſpirits:</hi> the other, is <hi>the changing of ſpirits:</hi> this later is a bleſſed conqueſt, not onely to thoſe who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113435:9"/> but to thoſe who are overcome. The Parliament hath cauſe this day to bleſſe God for ſubjecting evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to them; but I may ſay, (without a figure or the leaſt ſtrain to truth) moſt of thoſe ſpirits are ſubject to them but as the Divels were ſubject to the Diſciples; 'tis but a forced and a conſtrained ſubjection, a chain is put upon their ſpirits, their ſpirits are not changed: they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, becauſe they cannot longer prevail and have their wills. We have cauſe (I ſay) to bleſſe God for this. The Prophet foretelleth what ſubjection ſhall be made at laſt to the Church, (<hi>Iſa. 60. 14) The ſonnes alſo of them that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted thee, ſhall come bending unto thee, and all that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee, ſhall bow themſelves down at the ſoles of thy feet,</hi> &amp;c. It is a mercy when men are made to bow; but it will be our glory, when all ſhall willingly bow to the throne of truth and holineſſe, to the Scepter of judgement and righteouſnes. It is well for us when fire and ſword makes enemies ſubmit; but it will be beſt with all, when repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and ſorrow for ſinne, when honeſty and grace makes men ſubmit. When men ſubmit from a change of their principles, not from a change only of providences: from a change wrought in their hearts, not from a change wrought in their ſtates. God hath fulfilled that prayer of the Pſalmiſt, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 30.) in our dayes. He hath <hi>rebuked the company of Spear-men,</hi> or (as the letter of the Hebrew gives it) <hi>the beaſts of the reeds,</hi> of which ſpeares were anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently made, and to which they are (in faſhion) like. Theſe beaſts of the reeds God hath rebuked, as alſo <hi>the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Buls</hi> (boiſterous, men) <hi>and the calves of the people</hi> (ſimple men) till many of them <hi>have ſubmitted themſelves with peeces of ſilver</hi> (to make their compoſitions <hi>and hath ſcattered the people who delighted in warre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that is, ſuch as would not ſubmit. This the Lord hath done already.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113435:9"/>
            <p>Now let this be a word to you, <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> who are ſo highly intereſted in the publique affaires, let your deſigne be eſpecially to make ſpirits ſubject to you by a willing ſubjection. Endeavour that in the day of your power as it is in the day of Chriſts power (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.) the people may be not only ſubject, but willing; That their ſubjection to the Parliament may be (in its ſphear) like that of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to the Goſpel, (2 Cor. 9. 13.) <hi>a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsed ſubjection, not a forced ſubjection.</hi> The greateſt part of your warre is with the ſpirits of men; it is ſaid of <hi>Saul, (1 Sam 16. 14.) That the ſpirit of the Lord departed from him, and an evil ſpirit from the Lord troubled him,</hi> that evil ſpirit was it which encreaſed his envy, and continued the warre againſt <hi>David.</hi> The Phariſees ſaid of Chriſt, (<hi>Joh. 10. 20. He hath a Divel, and is mad:</hi> every man (as the learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Mede</hi> obſerveth in one of his <hi>Diatribes</hi>) was thought to have a Divel in thoſe times, who did things fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and madly. Many ſuch furious ones are amongſt us, of whom we may well ſay, <hi>they have a Devil, for they are mad;</hi> they would never run ſuch mad courſes, did not an evil ſpirit enrage and hurry them.</p>
            <p>I might deſcribe many of theſe evil ſpirits; I will name a few.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the evil ſpirits of <hi>pride and contention.</hi> Theſe are the cauſe of wars and troubles in all nations. <hi>Becauſe of pride commeth contention.</hi> Natural ſpirits do not generate, but theſe ſpirits doe. The ſpirit of pride procreates the ſpirit of contention. Were we more humble, we might he more quiet; and the reaſon why ſo few have their deſires, is, becauſe ſo many reſolve to have their wills.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the evil ſpirits of <hi>envy and malice.</hi> Many are ſick of other mens health, and poor with other mens rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113435:10"/> and diſappointed by their neighbours ſucceſſe: impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent envy thus rotting the bones, breeds rancorous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in the heart, and both break out to the danger of the whole body. Could we bear the good of others, it would be better for our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the evil ſpirits of <hi>errour and falſehood</hi> unquiet our times. What a calmnes would follow if theſe were caſt out of every heart. A ſpirit of errour deſerves every mans abhorrence: though a perſon erring may challenge our patience. This ſpirit of errour is extream bad: but a ſpirit of falſe-hood is farre worſe. All agree, they may be ſomewhat borne with, who erre conſcienciouſly, (which is very poſſible) But they are inſufferable, who act unconſcionably, which is very uſuall.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the evil ſpirits of <hi>jealouſie and ſelf-love.</hi> I put theſe together, becauſe ungrounded jealouſie of others is commonly accompanied with inordinate love of our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſpirit of jealouſy</hi> (ſo it is called) <hi>Numb.</hi> 5. 14. is the diſturber of Kingdomes as well as of families. And <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love</hi> is ſet in the head of that <hi>black Army,</hi> which is prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied to make <hi>perillous times in the laſt dayes,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>Above all, there is an evil ſpirit which I may call the <hi>Beelzebub of this generation, or the Prince of Devils,</hi> that is <hi>a ſpirit of diviſion.</hi> This workes in all places almoſt in all hearts. Diviſion ſeems to be the great deſigne againſt us; That while we act ſimply, we may be univerſally o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome. This ſpirit is grown ſo cunning, that it can work diſtances by a motion, or an endeavour for union. While many are ready to ſay and pray, <hi>Let us not divide, though we cannot agree;</hi> yet are moſt ready to divide upon every diſagreement. And while it is almoſt in every mans mouth, <hi>Let us be one in affection, though we cannot be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113435:10"/> one in opinion,</hi> yet every man almoſt acts, as if neither one earth nor one heaven could hold thoſe who hold not one opinion.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſpirits and ſuch as theſe are the troublers of our peace: and unleſſe theſe ſpirits are changed, or at leaſt chained all fleſh is in danger to periſh among us. The chaining of them may make our times peaceable; but the change of them will make our times glorious. How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſhould we be, if a ſpirit of humility and meeknes, of charity and brotherly kindnes; of truth and uprightnes, of ſelf-deniall and ardent deſires of maintaining the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace, poſſeſſed all our hearts?</p>
            <p>Right Honourable, if once you had received letters of credit and good aſſurance, that evil ſpirits were foiled, and had received a blow, either in the eaſt or weſt, north or ſouth, and that a better ſpirit were acting in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you would have cauſe to keep ſuch a day of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving and praiſe to God, as you never kept to this day. Till a conqueſt be gained over the ſpirits of men, our conqueſts over men will not give us reſt. And though I would not leſſen the mercies of God, eſpecially at this time when we come to bleſſe him for ſo great a mercy, as we this day commemorate: yet I ſay, what heart almoſt can we have to bleſſe God, or be enlarged in his Praiſes for ſubduing bodies, Towns and Cities, while legions of evil ſpirits in camp in ſo many places, and quarter in ſo many hearts. A conqueſt over ſpirits, is the glory of all our other conqueſts.</p>
            <p>Therefore (Right Honourable) I ſay it again, let the ſtreſſe of your counſels and deſignes be laid againſt theſe ſpirits. The ſword may work an unwilling ſubjection; God only can work a ſubjection of the will. Yet two
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113435:11"/> things done by men, by men (as your <hi>Selves</hi> are) in Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Authority, will contribute much towards this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. Firſt, juſtice done, and done impartially, for, and upon all. Secondly, countenance and encouragement gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to all that are good, and do good. When ſpirits are overcome upon theſe terms, I know not who ſhall have greater cauſe to rejoyce, they who are ſubject, or they who have made them ſo.</p>
            <p>But though this would be matter of great joy, yet this muſt not be either the totall or the chief matter of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing. The next words of the Text lead us to this modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of our joy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Notwithſtanding in this rejoyce not, but rather rejoyce that your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The connexion tells us, <hi>we are very apt to overact out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts, and overjoy our worldly joy.</hi> The whole world is too narrow for the heart of man; Our joys may quickly exceed it, and we be more taken with it, then it is worth. Chriſt ſaw his Diſciples in danger of taking in too much of the world. The creature gets quickly into our hearts, and our hearts may quickly get beyond the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Onely God is an object which we cannot overjoy, or ſtretch our affections too far towards. It is ſeldom that we can rejoyce at all (we can never rejoyce enough while we are in the fleſh) in ſpirituall mercies, and it is ſeldom but we rejoyce too much in temporall. The world is ſo much of kin to us, and is ſo like us: worldly comforts ſuit us ſo well, and are ſo neer us that while we deal about them, we need a bridle, not a ſpurre.</p>
            <p>It is one of the greateſt priviledges which we wait for in Heaven, that our affections may bee ever kept in a due temper. There we ſhall love and rejoyce in nothing but God, or for God. And as we cannot love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113435:11"/> in God too much, ſo there we ſhall not love or rejoice in him too little. But while we converſe with creatures, we are apt to feed too heartily upon them, and to drink larger draughts of the wine of their conſolation then becomes us. The way to leſſen earthly joy, is to ſtirre up heavenly. As when love is divided upon many objects of the ſame worth, it cannot run ſo ſtrongly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one: ſo much more, when it is carryed to a more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy object, will it abate towards thoſe which are leſſe worthy. The Text is clear for it, teaching us;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That our receits of temporall and outward mercies, ſhould be but as an occaſion to raiſe our hearts higher in rejoycing for ſpirituall and eternall mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Notwithſtanding rejoyce not in this, that ſpirits are ſubject to you, but rather rejoyce, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All creatures and comforts on earth, ſhould be but as foils to ſet off the glory of Heaven. How good is grace and glory, if there be ſo much good in nature? It was Chriſts art to do thus, when he came to the well, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. and was thirſty, he riſeth from that water and the thirſt he had to it, to tell the woman of another water, which if ſhe could once drink, ſhe ſhould never thirſt. And <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 27. when he ſaw his followers ſo hungry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loaves of bread, which is periſhing meat, He took an occaſion to exhort them <hi>to labour for the meat that peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth not, but endures to everlaſting life.</hi> It is ſafeſt for us (as well as our duty) to beſtow the ſtrength of our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes upon our ſinnes, and the ſtrength of our joyes upon Chriſt.</p>
            <p>There is a double ground or reaſon, why we ſhould thus in our receits of temporall mercies, get our hearts off, or get our hearts above them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſpirituall mercies are the beſt mercies. They
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113435:12"/> are beſt in their nature, and they are beſt in their enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they are laſting mercies. The joy of the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, all his joy is but for a moment: and the worldly joy of the ſincere is but for a moment. That cannot laſt long whoſe bottom and foundation cannot laſt long; <hi>the world paſſeth away, and the faſhion of it;</hi> therefore the joy that ariſeth out of the world and the goodly faſhions of it, muſt needs paſſe away too. When one of the Ancients ſtood by <hi>Caeſars tomb,</hi> who had the honour (while he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) of ſo many victories and triumphs; he cries out, <hi>O Caeſar, where is now thy magnificence? where are thy Armies? where are thy Trophies? where are the Towns and Cities which thou haſt overcome?</hi> They are all paſt away. We may ſay as much of all our victories and deliverances, of beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the enemy in the field, of beating him out of ſtrong holds; in a few yeers what will become of all theſe things, and of the worldly iſſues of them? Time will eat ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the remembrance of this glory. <hi>Solomon</hi> doth not ſo much queſtion, as chide, (<hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 5.) <hi>wilt thou ſet thine heart upon that which is not?</hi> Can a man be in danger of ſetting his heart upon that, which hath not a being? <hi>Creatures have ſo little being, that they are ſaid to have no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo have all creature-comforts: wilt thou ſet thine heart upon that which is not?</hi> How long will the comfort of conqueſts and victories laſt, that we ſhould rejoyce onely, or much in them?</p>
            <p>Secondly, if we confine our joyes to theſe, we are in a double danger. In a danger, Firſt of growing proud of, and confident upon our victories; nothing keeps the heart low but joy in the higheſt things. Ioy in low things makes the heart ſinfully) high, and joy in high things makes the heart (graciouſly low. That's the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why the men of the world boaſt themſelves in their riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113435:12"/> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the reaſon I ſay, why they grow proud of theſe things, is becauſe they have nothing elſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in.</p>
            <p>Secondly by joying much in the creature, we are in danger to ſurfeit upon the creature, or to grow wanton with it. When the minde is ſteeped in our ſenſes, we can hardly get the taſte off again. We follow the world ſo much, becauſe it gives us ſo little: we are unceſſant in purſuing earthly contents, becauſe we ſtill hope for more, and are unſatisfied with what we have. But when the heart once taſtes of ſpirituall dainties, it findes ſatisfaction; and being ſatisfied, deſires to taſte them ſtill: fulnes and hunger, ſatisfaction and appetite being perpetually inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable. The taſte of heavenly things is ſo high and quick, that all beſides taſtes flat and dreggiſh. No man (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>deſireth new wine, having drunk the old, for he ſaith the old is better.</hi> Earthly comforts will not hold ſo fair a proportion to heavenly, as new wine doth to old. They differ not in degree onely, but in kinde. The creature hath alwaies an unſatisfyingneſſe in it, and at the laſt it will have a bitternes. <hi>Prov. 25. 27. To eat much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is not good,</hi> (if a man eat honey long or often, it will not be honey to him) <hi>ſo for men to ſearch their own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is not glory,</hi> thus we tranſlate it; but the text is well rendred, and cloſer to the Originall thus, <hi>To multiply to eat honey, or to eat much honey is not good, but the laſt of glory is glory.</hi> The Saints ſhall feed to eternity upon glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that will be alwaies glory: but honey, the beſt of worldly comforts will be gall, if you feed much upon them. Therefore correct your appetites after the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; make your joy in worldly things an occaſion and a ſtep to ſpirituall; doing ſo, three effects will flow from ſuch joy.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113435:13"/>
            <p>Firſt, ſuch joys will make us very holy. Joy in worldly things alone, leaves us as worldly as it findes us: but if we mix it with ſpirituall, holines will mingle with our ſpirits. <hi>The Lord promiſes to give his people beauty for aſhes, the oyl of joy for mourning, the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſse,</hi> (Iſa. 61. 3.) here is the Lords joy: we have the effect of this in the next words: <hi>That they may be called, trees of righteouſnes, the planting of the Lord, that he may be glorified.</hi> If we rejoyce in the Lord, we ſhall rejoyce to the glory of the Lord; <hi>Trees of righteouſnes have their fruit in holines.</hi> It is a ſad thing to ſee what fruit the joy of moſt brings forth, intemperance, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, ſenſuality, ſecurity, injuſtice, fruits of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Ioy thus temper'd makes us ſtrong to ſerve the Lord; joy in the Lord carryes us to the Lord, <hi>Neh. 8. 10.) The joy of the Lord is our ſtrength.</hi> Joy in the world weakens and flats our ſpirits: joy in the Lord, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens as well as purifies, and makes us at once holy and active.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Such joy makes us more then ſtrong, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing zealous for the Lord. After the people in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> time had feaſted ſeven dayes, the ſtory ſaith (2 <hi>Chron. 30. 23.) The whole aſsembly took counſel to keep other ſeven days, and they kept other ſeven days with gladneſſe.</hi> Here were ſeven and ſeven days of feaſting: it ſeems they loved feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well; but the effect aſſures us, they did more then eat, drink and make merry at their feaſt. Their joy and gladnes, was not in corne, and wine and good chear: No, it was joy in the Lord, and in his goodnes; for they preſently act like thoſe that had rejoyced in the Lord. Many in one dayes feaſt loſe the memory of the Lord, and of their own duty: but theſe in fourteendayes feaſting
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113435:13"/> forgot neither. The firſt verſe of the next chapt. is clear for it; <hi>Now when all this was finiſhed,</hi> (a feaſt of fourteen dayes continuance) what did they then? ſome might think them furniſht for any kinde of wickednes: That they had eat and drunk out, not only their graces, but their wits, that now they were fit only to <hi>throw the houſe out at the windowes</hi> (as we ſay) no, <hi>they threw ſin out at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,</hi> ſo ſaith the ſtory, <hi>for when all this was finiſhed, all Iſrael that were preſent, went out to the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>and brake the images in pieces, and cut down the groves, and threw down the high places and the altars out of all</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Benjamin, <hi>in</hi> Ephraim <hi>alſo and</hi> Manaſſeh, <hi>untill they had utterly destroyed them all,</hi> &amp;c. They made a perfect work of caſting out whatſoever was diſpleaſing unto God. Had they only taken pleaſure in creatures, they had never done what was ſo pleaſing unto God. Every thing we rejoyce moſt in, we are moſt zealous for. We ſhould rejoyce more in the God of our mercies, then in the mercies of God; and while we do ſo, we ſhall alſo rejoyce more in our duties, then in our mercies.</p>
            <p>We are this day called to rejoyce in an outward mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the reducing of a ſtrong City. In this victory <hi>ſpirits are made ſubject:</hi> in overco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming evil men, we overcome evil ſpirits. I delight not to be a cenſurer at any time, leaſt of all at this; yet we know what a ſtrain, what a generation of men theſe were. If evil ſpirits have been made ſubject in any part of the Kingdom, ſome were in this. That place is diſpoſſeſſed of many untoward ſpirits who poſſeſſed it long, and caſt much of it into the fire: Theſe are now caſt out by ſword and fire; But chiefly by thoſe better weapons of prayer and faſting. Chriſt ſaid of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, <hi>You are of your father the Devil,</hi> (Joh. 8. 44.) And <hi>Polycarp</hi> in the Church ſtory, called <hi>Marcion,</hi> the <hi>firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113435:14"/> of the Devil.</hi> All ungodly men are of the ſame line and race. There is very little difference between the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and a wicked man, but fleſh and bones; Hence in common ſpeech we call very wicked men <hi>Devils incarnate;</hi> I may ſay (without breach of charity) <hi>Devils incarnate</hi> are made ſubject at this day, and their ſubjection is the ſubject of this days rejoycing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Notwithstanding in this rejoyce not, that theſe ſpirits are ſubject to you;</hi> rejoyce not much in this. Chriſt (<hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 23.) ſpeaks of ſome who had the power and priviledge, to make Devils in kinde ſubject to them, many (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall come to me in that day, and ſay, Lord, Lord, we have prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in thy name, and in thy name we have caſt out Devils, and we have done many wonderfull works;</hi> yet theſe wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workers had little cauſe to rejoyce. It is poſſible for a man not only to ſubdue the evil ſpirits of men, but to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due evil ſpirits themſelves, (take them in their naturall notion) and yet to have no cauſe of rejoycing; I am ſure they had not; becauſe while they had power over De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, themſelves were under the power of the Devil. The Devils were ſubject to them, yet they were the Devils ſervants. Chriſt diſcards them under that relation, <hi>ver. 24. Depart from me, ye that work iniquity;</hi> and whoſe work is that? I know none who put men to that imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or drudgery rather, but only Satan, <hi>his ſervice is the work of iniquity;</hi> ſome may caſt out Devils who take in the work of the Devil. Hence, they who have caſt out Devils, may be caſt to the Devil. Had we this power to caſt out Devils in kinde, our joy would quickly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, unleſſe we have learned to out-joy it. To further which deſigne upon theſe worldly joyes, I would ſpeak a few words.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to thoſe who have more to rejoyce in then vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113435:14"/> over men and cities. Secondly, to thoſe who, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a true account, have no more to rejoyce in.</p>
            <p>To the former my motion is. Make the mercies of this day an occaſion to act your joy upon eternall mercies. It is poſſible for a godly man to ſuffer the ſtream of his joy to run more then is meet in a worldly chanell. The beſt have reaſon enough to be jealous over their own hearts.</p>
            <p>You are called to rejoyce, and I am not a forbidder, I would be a helper of your joy. Joy is comely, and the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of praiſe in faſhion this day. Therefore ſay to your ſouls, Let us rejoyce, and let all that is within us bleſſe the holy name of God for the great things he hath done for us; when you have done this, ſpeak again to your ſouls in the language of the text; O our ſouls, rejoyce in better things then theſe, Let us rejoyce that our names are written in Heaven. Drink not too large draughts of thoſe worldly comforts, go to that which is better and richer wine, take your fill in the conſolations of God.</p>
            <p>To quicken this, I might ſhew you many moſt deſirable objects. I will only hint a few: rejoyce that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath made a perfect conqueſt for you over ſpirituall enemies, rejoyce that Chriſt hath ſpoiled principalities and powers, and dragged the Devil at his chariot of triumph, when he aſcended up to heaven: rejoyce that Chriſt hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come death and ſubdued the grave: rejoyce that Chriſt died to free you from death, and hath brought life and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality to light through the Goſpel: rejoyce that Chriſt hath ſtrengthned you to withſtand temptations, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you power to conquer paſſion: rejoyce that Chriſt by accompliſhing the work of redemption, hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the pardon of ſin, peace with God, and an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which ſadeth not away; rejoyce that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113435:15"/> a City for you, which no Armies ſhall lay ſiege un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or ſhoot an arrow againſt: rejoyce that he hath provided an eſtate for you that ſhall never be ſpent, and a Kingdom which ſhall never be ſhaken. When you hear men are made ſubject to men, rejoyce that Chriſt hath made you ſubject to himſelf: when you hear ſtrong holds are taken, rejoyce that the ſtrong holds of ſin are bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered down and taken: that there is not an evil imagination in you, but if it ſtir, you have a weapon in readines, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge that diſobedience. When you heare how they who have fought againſt Chriſt are brought low, rejoyce that you are not fighting againſt Chriſt, that you are not trampling his precious blood under your feet, that you delight not in that, by which the holy ſpirit is grieved. Let looſe your affections upon theſe better, higher and more noble objects: rejoyce here as much as you can. <hi>It is altogether below the state of a Saint to rejoyce only in things that are below.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I would offer a word to thoſe who have none of theſe mercies to rejoyce in, who have nothing but a world to rejoyce in. Poor ſouls! what do you rejoycing? what do you keeping dayes of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for victories obtained againſt men and Cities? can you rejoyce on theſe terms? can you rejoyce in hopes of peace upon earth, when war is proclaimed againſt you in Heaven? Can you rejoyce that Cities are ſubdued, when your hearts are unſubdued? Can you give thanks this day that the City of <hi>Cheſter</hi> is taken in, after five or ſix Moneths ſiege, when as your own hearts have ſtood out ſeven and ſeven yeers ſiege againſt the continuall batteries of the Word? Can you rejoyce that ſtrong holds are demoliſhed, when you fortify and gariſon ſtrong holds with legions of luſts, with covetouſnes, pride, ſelf-love,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113435:15"/> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When you victuall them, and lay in provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to make them hold out as long as you live againſt Jeſus Chriſt, Can you rejoyce? Rather go home and weep over theſe mercies; weep over victories and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes. Let your laughter be turned into mourning, and your ſong of joy into a lamentation. Leave joy to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Will you keep a day of rejoycing, who are likely to mourn and weep for ever? reſt not in reſtleſſe things, live not in an eſtate wherein you are unfit to dy. All the world is not worth the rejoycing in, unleſſe ye have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe to rejoyce in. God forbid (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal 6. 14.) That I ſhould rejoyce in any thing, ſave in the croſse of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If you have not Chriſt to rejoyce in, God forbids all your other joyes: and your ſorrowes will be the more bitter to you hereafter, by how much your joyes have been now more ſweet. Weep, (if any ſuch now offer at this duty) weep proud hearts, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous hearts, envious ſpirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> weep till you bring Chriſt the ſpoyl of your luſts, till you ſhew him the ruines of your corruptions: weep till you bring him broken hearts, till you bring him wills ſtooping to his word, and ſpirits made ſubject to his ſpirit: weep till you finde ſuch matter of joy as the text ſpeaks of, an evidence that your names are written in heaven.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But rather rejoyce that your names are written in Heaven.</l>
               <l>The names of the Saints are written in Heaven.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If ſo, Then, firſt they are ſafe, their eſtate is ſetled, their names are taken into the liſt of bleſſednes.</p>
            <p>2. They are honourable. A man under diſgrace hath his name written in the duſt: but to have a name enrolled in Heaven, is an expreſſion of the higheſt honour.</p>
            <p>3. They ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113435:16"/> ſhall be able to obliterate or raſe out a name that is written in Heaven. <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports of <hi>Herod,</hi> that he burnt all the genealogies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that himſelf might be miſtaken for a <hi>Jew.</hi> But no <hi>Herod,</hi> with his power and pride, ſhall ever burn or deface the roll of election: Names written in that ſhall not be blotted out: The land of forgetfullnes lyes all on this ſide heaven.</p>
            <p>Is not this a ground of great joy, and ſtrong conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Saints? Poſſibly their names are blotted here upon the earth, but there is no blot upon them in heaven. God doth not delight to take notice of the failings and miſcarriages of his ſervants, much leſſe will he deface their names, when they miſcarry. In Scripture, ſome miſcarriages of the Saints are recorded (which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are blots) but the end why they are recorded is for our warning, not for their ſhame: which yet is the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of moſt on earth, who induſtriouſly write books of the <hi>Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rata's,</hi> whether in opinion or in practice. It it very dangerous to blot names which are written in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Chriſt would not have any ſin flattered in any man, but, Chriſt would not have all ſins diſcovered in all men; therefore he hath provided a covering, not that which is the ordinary covering, ſelf-flattery, or the flattery of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The covering he hath provided is, <hi>charity, charity covereth a multitude of ſins,</hi> (1 Pet. 4. 8.) Surely their chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is very narrow, or if it be not narrow, I wonder what uſe they put it to, who will hardly cover one infirmity of an offending brother. Yea, ſome are ſo greedy after of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, that though they are covered, yet they uncover them, and are ſo far from caſting a garment over what appears, that they pull off the very ſeals of ſecrecy to make all appear.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113435:16"/>
            <p>It doth not become <hi>men</hi> to do ſo, much leſſe <hi>Saints.</hi> But as to ſuffer theſe blots is the patience of the Saints on earth, ſo it is their joy to hear that there are no blots upon their names in heaven. Be of good comfortt, though men blot, God will not. For as he ſpeaks to <hi>Moſes;</hi> deſiring not a blot upon his name, but the blotting out of his name, <hi>Exod. 32. 32. Blot me, I pray thee, out of thy book which thou haſt written.</hi> Blot thee, <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaith God? No, I will never blot thee, I will put no blots upon ſuch names as thine; much leſſe blot ſuch names out. There was a failing in that ſpeech of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſome interpret that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of his to be his blot: yet God doth not put it as a blot upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> but ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever hath ſinned againſt me, him will I blot out of my book.</hi> God is ſo far from deſiring to blot the names of his people, that he will not blot them, though they themſelves ſhould deſire it. He will neither blot them out of his book; nor blot them in his book; He will do neither, he keeps the names of his Saints fair written for ever.</p>
            <p>Then (which is the laſt point) <hi>It is matter of great joy to have our names written in Heaven. This is a priviledge worth the having, To be in Gods books.</hi> Heer's honour indeed, <hi>To be of the Church of the firſt-borne, whoſe names are written in Heaven,</hi> Heb. 12. 23. They who have their names written higheſt in the earth, ſhould be moſt deſirous to have their names written thus high. They that are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and great, they that are men <hi>of name in the world,</hi> as the giants are intitled, (<hi>Gen. 6. 4. at that time there were men of name, men of renown</hi>) ſuch ſhould be moſt ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of being men of name above.</p>
            <p>My Lords, your names are written very high here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. And it is my prayer that your names may be written
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113435:17"/> higher, that even your earthly honours and dignities may encreaſe, and that your <hi>Fame</hi> may be as an ointment poured out, perfuming not only this Kingdom, but the world, with your juſt and heroicall actions. Yet let it not ſuffice <hi>You</hi> (ſuch ambition is a vertue) I ſay let it not ſatisfie <hi>You,</hi> who have ſo great a name upon the earth, to have a name upon the earth; I would not have it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the meaneſt man upon earth, much leſſe ſhould it content <hi>your Lordſhips</hi> who have <hi>Great eſtates, Great digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Great titles, Great families, Great Anceſtors, Great ſpirits,</hi> to have names narrowed up to this earth, this little molehill of earth. It is a duty for the greateſt perſons, (if God call them to it) to be contented with a little of the earth: but it is a ſinne for the meaneſt perſon to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with all the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luther</hi> ſpoke himſelf <hi>a Protestant indeed,</hi> while he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, <hi>I will never be ſatisfied with the creature. The great world</hi> is not big enough for the epitome of it, <hi>The little world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lords, there are not very many names (if we ſpeak comparatively) written in heaven at all; the roll is not large which contains thoſe inſcriptions. And the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks of the <hi>Noble and Honourable</hi> (which it doth but of one ſort of men more) with a diminution, (1 <hi>Cor. 1. 26.) Not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called.</hi> There are not very many in all called, and of thoſe there are not <hi>many mighty, nor many noble;</hi> This ſhould not be a diſcouragement, but a ſpurre to your Honours. Do not think that this Scripture ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitates any of <hi>You</hi> to be left out: many will not be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, though all your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> be. There are <hi>Nobles</hi> enow in the world, in whom this text will be verified
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113435:17"/> and made good, though it be not in any of your <hi>Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able number.</hi> Let it fill all your hearts with holy jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies concerning your ſelves, not with deſpondencies, much leſſe deſpairs concerning any of your ſelves.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſaid to his <hi>twelve Diſciples, One of you ſhall betray me,</hi> it put them all upon this ſuſpicion, who it ſhould be, and one ſaid, <hi>Master, is it I? another, Master, is it I?</hi> When the Holy Ghoſt in this Scripture ſaith, <hi>Not many noble are called,</hi> it ſhould put all that are Noble upon this Inquiſition, <hi>Lord, am I called? Lord, am I? Is my name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Heaven? is mine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be asked: but with what ſpectacles ſhall we reade at ſuch a diſtance? How ſhall we diſcern whether our names are written in heaven or no?</p>
            <p>I intend not to enter upon a diſcourſe of ſignes and tokens; but as the Apoſtle anſwers them, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 6.) who were making Quaeries about Chriſt, <hi>Say not in thine heart, Who ſhall aſcend up to heaven?</hi> they made great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, how to get neer Chriſt, how to know him: <hi>ſay not in thine heart</hi> (ſaith he) have not theſe reaſonings, <hi>Who ſhall aſcend up to heaven?</hi> With what ladders ſhall we ſcale the clouds? or with what wings ſhall we ſoar up thither? Trouble not thy ſelf (ſaith the Apoſtle) with theſe thoughts, thou ſhalt not be put to ſo long a journey, <hi>for the word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart the word of faith which we preach.</hi> I ſay likewiſe to theſe <hi>Quaeriſts,</hi> Say not in your hearts, who ſhall aſcend up to heaven to ſee, whether his name be written there, or how ſhall we ſend a meſſenger thither to ſearch the records? You may ſave that journey, the word is neer you, the word is before you, even the word of faith and of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which we preach.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113435:18"/>
            <p>If the name of God be written in your hearts, your names are written in Heaven.</p>
            <p>If you in your actions daily write out a copy of this book, aſſure your ſelves the hand of God hath written you in his book. The lives of the Saints ſhould be a continued copying out of the book of God. He that writes out the book of God in his life, may reſt aſſured his name is written in the book of life.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113435:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
